All right, there friends, after loops we come across arrays and have a good little
discussion about them. Why do we use them? How do we use them in Java? And just to start
quickly, why would you use arrays is because let's say now your requirement is to save multiple
values at the same time. With a variable, a bit of any data type, you can just store one value
at a time. And then you can change the value, but it has to be of the same data type of which
you have declared that variable of. But with arrays that give you the flexibility of storing
multiple values at the same time of that same data type, right? And in Java, how can we
declare an initialize an array? So there are actually a few ways to do that. Let's go on and
quickly create a new class. Again, I'll just say control n Java class and let's just call it
arrays fun. So we go on with the customary, the traditional main method. And now how can you declare
an array in Java? As I said, few ways to do that, the first one is you just say the data type
or let's just stick to type because as you will find shortly later in the codes that there are
more types in Java. So we not just specify this as a data type, but more generically as a type.
So I'll just say type identifier. And then you would say that identifier to new the keyword
new and we'll have a detailed discussion about the keyword new in some time. But for now,
this is the syntax and you'll say type and then the dimension or the size. That is how many values
you want to be this variable of array to be holding at a particular time. That is what you define
here. And then you put in the square representation brackets of the array right here so that it doesn't
look like a normal variable, but an array variable. Remember, the representation is these
scale brackets, but never ever define the size here, the dimension here that doesn't have to be
done at the declaration time, but always on the right side at the initialization time, right?
And following this syntax, whatever your type is currently, we'll just stick to data types,
but when I tell you about more types that you can use to declare a variable, then you would know
you can have that kind of an array as well. And that's perfectly possible. And just to pause here,
I just hope that you're having a good time understanding these Java concepts from absolute scratch,
right? That's what I promised at the start of this course. And we will slowly go on into details,
dive deep into these concepts, take the discussion forward, but just do your hands on properly,
go through the exercises. And if you have any questions, make sure you reach out. All right, so coming
back to the discussion following this, following this syntax. So let's say we have to declare a
data type or an array of type, let's say long. So how would you do that? You'll say long, and then
you can say for example, let's call it values, that's appropriate, and that's declaration,
and then we have to initialize it. At the time of initialization, we don't put the square brackets here,
because it's already done, that would be redundant. So we'll say values equal to the keyword new,
and then again, long, and you say five for a start. Now you've got to get an array variable,
which can hold five values of type long at one time, right? And then you can go on and
initialize it. How do you initialize it? You say with the index, right? And this is where you put
in the index, and arrays in Java like other languages, the index is start with zero, and the last
index is dimension minus one. In this case, that would be four. So we'll start with zero, and I'll say
for example, five, 67. Similarly, we'll just paste it a few times, I'll say values of one, two,
some other value. And then we'll say values of two, two, three, four, for example. Now values of
three and values of four, they would not have any values, that is, I'm coming to, what do variables
have in Java as the default value? But for a start, there is no such concept as a garbage value
in Java, right? There is a value or there is not. And with array variables, they have default values
depending on the type of the array variable, right? And in this case, it's long, that means they
would have zero and zero. If you don't initialize them, but for now, let's go on and initialize them.
So I'll say three, two, let's say some other value, four, two, some other value. And then let's
say mistakenly, if you say five, and the thing to observe it is, it would not be a error, it would
not be a compile time error, but it would be an exception at runtime. Why does this compile is because
for the syntax, it just checks that the array name is values, you have declared that,
and then five, that means it just expects you to put in a number. And that's what you're doing.
At runtime, it sees that this is out of bounds. This index doesn't exist because guess what?
The last index of this array was four, because it started with zero, but IntelliJ,
the name is IntelliJ, that is, IntelliJ is built in, it gives you that that that warning in yellow,
if you hold on this, it says array index out of bounds, but it's just a warning, right? If you
run this, you'll get an array index out of bounds, exception at runtime. I'll just say for now,
exception at runtime. But it just compiles perfectly fine, right? So now you have
initialized it, let's go on and run this, and off you go exception in thread means Java or
land dot array index out of bounds exception index five out of bounds for length five. That means the
last one is four, you click on this blue, it takes you exactly to that point. And for now,
what I'll do is I'll just comment this out, right? So once you have initialized it, now we need to
get the values out of the array and then print them out. And I'll just say a south, for example,
our values of, let's say three. So we'll get the value at location full, remember, because it starts
with zero index. So I'll just say run and gives us two, two, three, three, four, because we had put
that at the third index in that area. But we will need to display it or to work with an array
individually with all indexes. We can just use our good friend's the loops, whether or for,
or a buy or a do while or this time will have one more loop, which was specifically introduced for
arrays. And that is coming for you in the next video. But for now, I'll just get rid of this and use
the traditional for loop. But in your case, you can just go on and use the value as well. And I'll
say int index appropriately named, I'll just start with zero. This is the starting point, I'll say
index is less than, I can say five, right? But guess what? Sometimes you would get these
arrays as values from a different method and you won't know the length. That's why it's always
handy. You use the inbuilt dot length, the inbuilt variable, which just gets you the dynamically
the length of that in, right? And I'll say index plus plus. And then we'll have it for loop body,
the warnings are gone. And I'll just say a sound, I'll say get me values of index.
And that's it. Right. So we started with the follow up for, let's see what the warnings it says
for loop can be replaced with the enhanced for loop, your right, Mr and Mrs, our miss,
IntelliJ, right? When I told you that is coming for you in the next video. But for now, we'll just
use a traditional for loop, right? And we start with zero. We say index is less than values or
length until then keep running the loop in iteration and then print me every value at that index
inside the area. Let's see if that gets me the job, then I'll just, and I'll also say a sound,
and I'll say values in area are. Let's run this and gets me all the values in the order in which
you had inserted them. 567, 1 3 6 7 2 3 3 4 2 2 3 4 and 3 6 5 7 for you. But again, you can just do
it with a while loop. And then line number 10 to 14. Again, I'm not doing the recommended things here.
I'm putting the hard coded values. You tell me what needs to be done here. Just recollect it
from your memory, what I have been telling you. That is, we need to always take, we should always
rather take values from user at runtime. And I've told you the best and the quickest way to do
that. And that's using the scanner class, right? And just go on, think over this program,
get the values from runtime, right? Just do it on your own. So for now, we have got this from the
indexes. That's perfectly fine. This is one of the basic ways to declare an array. What we did
is we declared an initialize on two different lines, but we can just go ahead and put this all
at on just one line. That is declaration and initialization on the same line. That's another way,
right? The third way would have been that is if, let's say I have to declare a variable or an
array of type care. And I see, let's just call it vowels, right? And now, let's say you know what
is going to be in this array before combined at the time you're writing the school. So that is where
Java comes up with the syntax, which is like other C style languages. And you put in like this.
That is the curly braces. And this is helpful. When you know it, what is going to be in the array,
before combined users go in and put in the individual values. And for characters, we put
the values in single quotes for numbers. No such thing, maybe, right? I'll just say, for example,
R or T, I'll say E, I'll say Y. So for now, you know what is in going to be in the array before
compiling this program. So this is another way to do this, right? And the length of this array
will now be three, it's dynamic. And then, yet, another way to declare an array in Java is quite a
handful in reality. And you just do directly like something like this. Let's say I need a integer array,
I'll say int like this and like this. And then I put in the values, I say 45, 967, 889 and 4.
And that just works. And for now, it doesn't work. It gives an error. I'll tell you why in something,
but this is one more way to declare an array in Java perfectly valid way. It's called array
inline creation rather to be appropriate. An anonymous array in line creation, right?
Hopefully valid, but it just works at one place in Java that is within parameters or within
arguments to a method. That's why it's not working here. Say it's not a statement. I've not put
in a semi colon, not needed. I'm not even naming this array, not needed, but it doesn't work here,
right? And that's why I'll just for now come in this out. I'll walk you through this example when
we are discussing methods or functions, right? But for now, just telling you, this is one another way
to declare an array in Java is called an anonymous array inline creation. Why are we going through
these concepts? The fundamentals, because in the age of AI in 2026, getting a good hold,
understanding fundamentals is more important than ever, right? So that is how we clear arrays,
multiple ways, how we initialize them, how we get values out of them, right? Display them or do
whatever you want to do with them. But in the next video, I'm going to tell you about a more
a modern way to traverse through any.